Alright,
בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody, בוקר טוב.
Boker Tov. Okay, today's דף Daf is ס"ז, Samech Zayin, well today's
official דף Daf is ס"ח. Samech Chet. We start at the bottom
of ס"ז עמוד א' Samech Zayin Amud Aleph and what we're going
to be, we pick up here which is on a whole, a
whole multiple debate of the תנאים. Tanna'im. We start with the משנה,
Mishna, which is the position of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, which is
that a woman who is pregnant married to a
כהן, Cohen, the עובר Uber sort of is אינו מאכיל, eino ma'achil,
does not let her eat תרומה Truma for her husband dies. It's
not considered yet that she has a child, but it's enough to
create a problem; it's also פוסל posel because he has a portion
of the slaves, he has a portion in the
slaves and as a עובר Uber cannot allow them, these slaves don't
eat by virtue of him. So let's take a look. We'll start
again from the ברייתא Braita quoted at the bottom of ס"ז עמוד
א'. Samech Zayin Amud Aleph. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught:
הניח בנים, Hiniach banim, if a woman left over
sons and no,
a כהן Cohen and no, and his wife was not pregnant. אלו
ואלו אוכלים. Eilu ve'eilu ochlin. The woman can eat and the woman's
slaves can eat and the husband's slaves can eat, because there's a
child, so the child entitles the woman to eat and there's no
problem for the slaves eating, they're own, all owned by the heirs
of the כהן. Cohen. הניח מעוברת, Hiniach muberet, if she's pregnant and
no children are born yet. אלו ואלו אינם אוכלים. Eilu ve'eilu einam
ochlin. She can't eat by virtue of the fetus because she can
only eat if she has a born child, and they can't eat
because they're partly owned by the fetus and therefore, or they're fully
owned by the fetus depending on if they're girls or whatever, anyway,
and therefore the fetus cannot allow them, they can't eat by virtue
of him. הניח בנים והניח מעוברת, Hiniach banim vehiniach muberet, there are
born children and she's pregnant. עבדי מלוג אוכלים, Avdei milug ochlin, her
servants can eat because she eats by virtue of the born children,
the pregnant child doesn't, the fetus doesn't affect her status, כדרך שהיא
אוכלת, kederech shehi ochelet, the same way her servants eat the same
way she eats. עבדי צאן ברזל לא יאכלו, Avdei tzon barzel lo
yochlu, but his servants, which apparently they're still his because she hasn't
yet collected, taken them yet back out of the estate, so his,
so the ones she brought in the dowry which are now his
servants, they don't eat מפני חלקו של עובר mipnei chelko shel uber
because the עובר Uber has a portion in what the born sons
have inherited and therefore creates the problem. עובר פוסל ואינו מאכיל, Uber
posel ve'eino ma'achil, he invalidates and he cannot feed. So he invalidates
even the ones, the slaves that are owned by the born children,
his presence makes a problem, but it's he does not entitle the
woman to eat, but she can eat by virtue of the other
born children. דברי רבי יוסי, Divrei Rabbi Yose, that's what רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose said. So that's consistent with the משנה, Mishna, just sort
of spelling it out. רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yishmael beRabbi
Yose omer, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael the son of רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose says משום אביו mishum aviv in the name of his
father: הבת מאכלת, הבן אינו מאכיל. Habat ma'achelet, haben eino ma'achil. The
daughter feeds, the son does not feed. Not at all clear what
that means; the גמרא Gemara will unpack that.
רבי שמעון בר יוחאי אומר, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai omer, רבי שמעון
בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai says: זכרים יאכלו כולם, נקבות לא
יאכלו.
Zcharim yochlu kulam,
nekeivot lo yochlu. So if there are only male children and she
is pregnant, then the slaves can eat. Okay? The male children can
eat and the slaves can eat and her slaves can eat. Now,
why is that? What if the עובר Uber is a boy and
has a portion in the estate, you know, in the slaves? Why
is this not a problem?
So basically the way the גמרא Gemara will explain it, but I'll
just tell you now, is because look, there's less than a fifty
percent chance that a live baby boy will be born from this
pregnant woman. Fifty percent chance it'll be a boy, fifty percent chance
it'll be a girl. If it's a girl, then that does not
create a problem in the, thank you, in the ownership of the
slaves because the slaves are owned by the live boys, the girl
doesn't have a portion in the estate. And if the fifty percent
chance that it's a boy, not every birth ends in a, not
every pregnancy ends in a live birth. So therefore there's a less
than a fifty percent chance, let's say it's a forty-eight percent chance
that a baby boy will be born. So therefore that's a מיעוט,
mi'ut, you don't have to concern yourself with a מיעוט mi'ut in
the majority of cases. מיעוט המצוי? mi'ut hamatzui?
Yeah, exactly. That's the position, okay? So if there are already male
children, we don't have to worry about the עובר Uber because it
might be a girl and won't affect the ownership and it might
be a boy and even if it's a boy it won't necessarily
be born alive. Then יאכלו כולם. yochlu kulam. נקבות, Nekeivot, if they're
girls, לא יאכלו, lo yochlu, שמא ימצא עובר זכר shema yimatze uber
zachar because maybe the boy will be a, the fetus will be
a male and then he'll have ownership over the slaves of course,
ואין לבנות במקום הבן כלום, ve'ein labanot bemakom haben klum, and the
girls won't have any portion of it. So the גמרא Gemara says,
מאי איריא שמא ימצא עובר זכר? Mai irya shema yimatze uber zachar?
I don't understand, if there are all girls and she's pregnant, it
doesn't matter whether the עובר Uber is a boy or a girl.
תיפוק ליה דנקבה נמי פסלה. Tei-poka-lei dene-keiva nami pasla. If she's a
girl, then she splits in the ownership of the slaves. And if
he's a boy, if he's a boy whatever, he gets all of
the ownership of the slaves. Either way, if right now there are
girls in the family and this woman is pregnant, this עובר Uber
will get a portion of the, of the estate, either all of
it or a piece of it. So the גמרא Gemara says... דאינקבא
נמי פסלה. de'inkeva nami pasla. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, חדא
ועוד קאמר. chada ve'od ka-amar. You're right, this and that. חדא, chada,
number one, דאינקבא נמי פסלה, de'inkeva nami pasla, even if she's a
girl, then because there's only girls right now, she'll get a portion
of the estate. ועוד שמא ימצא עובר זכר, ve'od shema yimatze oover
zachar, maybe there'll be a boy and then he'll get the whole
estate. ובין כך ובין כך לא יאכלו. uvein kach uvein kach lo
yochlu. Okay, so that's, so that's the, so that's the idea about,
you know, whether right now there are boys or girls, the position
of רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. Rabbi Yishmael be-Rabbi Yossi. But now the
גמרא Gemara wants to understand why when there are boys we don't
have to be concerned that the fetus is a boy and will
have a portion. So the גמרא Gemara says זכרים יאכלו, zcharim yochlu,
if it's only boys they can eat, or the slaves can eat.
ואיכא עובר? ve-ika oover? What about the fetus? Maybe that'll be a
boy and he'll have a portion? No, קסבר, kasavar, אין חוששין למיעוטא.
ein choshishin le-mi'uta. He's of the opinion you're not concerned yourself with
the minority, even though the minority is like a 48% minority, it's
pretty amazing, but nevertheless, you know, the possibility that it'll be born
as a live boy is less than 50%. So the גמרא Gemara
says ואיבעית אימא לעולם קסבר חוששין למיעוטא, ve-iba'it eima le'olam kasavar choshishin
le-mi'uta, or maybe you are concerned for this, especially when it's a
48% מיעוט. mi'ut. But דעבדינן ליה תקנתא. de-avdinan leh takanta. But maybe
he holds that there's a way of solving the problem of the
fetus and the fetus's ownership of the estate, partial ownership of the
estate. What's the way of solving it? דעבדינן ליה תקנתא... de-avdinan leh
takanta... where were we... דעבדינן ליה
תקנתא כרב נחמן אמר שמואל, de-avdinan leh takanta ke-Rav Nachman amar Shmuel,
like רב נחמן אמר שמואל. Rav Nachman amar Shmuel. דאמר רב נחמן
אמר שמואל, de-amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel, in a general case about
underage children when it comes to divide the estate,
יתומים שבאו לחלוק בנכסי אביהם, yetomim she-ba'u lachlok be-nichsei avihem, orphans who
are coming to divide the estate of their father. And some of
them are adults and some of them are not.
So בית דין מעמידין להם אפוטרופוס ובורר להם חלק יפה.
Beit Din ma'amidin lahem apotropus u-vorer lahem
chelek yafeh. בית דין Beit Din assigns for them an אפוטרופוס, apotropus,
some type of a, you know, what's a good English word for
this?
Caretaker, what? Executor? The executor is the one that takes the interests
of the dead. This is somebody that represents the interests of the
heir. Guardian. Steward. Okay. ובורר להם חלק יפה, u-vorer lahem chelek yafeh,
and picks for them in their, on their behalf, chooses for them
a good portion of the estate, sort of negotiates with the other
brothers in terms of how to divide it. הגדילו, higdilu, now what
happens if now they become adults? So יכולים למחות. yecholim limchot. So
according to the first... this opinion, they actually can then say, actually,
you know, we don't think he made the right choice for us,
and they can reverse his choice. So they really get the best
of both worlds. Right?
They get the years of...
I know, I know. Well, that's the next statement. But they get
the best of both worlds: somebody gets to choose for them and
they can keep it if it worked out in their interest and
if not, they can always reverse it. But רב נחמן דידיה אמר,
Rav Nachman didei amar, that's רב נחמן Rav Nachman in the name
of שמואל. Shmuel. רב נחמן Rav Nachman himself said הגדילו אין יכולים
למחות. higdilu ein yecholim limchot. No, no, no. Even once they become
adults they can't reverse the decision. דאם כן מה כח בית דין
יפה? de-im ken mah koach Beit Din yafeh? Because or else like
what's the point of, you know, where's the power of בית דין?
Beit Din? The power of בית דין Beit Din is to, you
know, assign them and make it and make it binding and make
it, yeah, that they fully represent them. Anyway, we're not going to
get into that debate, but the point is that he says that
we can actually designate a portion. So he says, ah, here's a
perfect solution to the problem of the עובר. oover. We have this
עובר, oover, we have these slaves that can't eat תרומה terumah now.
Let בית דין Beit Din go ahead and create a representative, an
אפוטרופוס apotropus for the עובר, oover, to pick out which portion of
the estate is his. Which slaves are his? Those slaves won't eat
and all the other slaves will eat. And that's why when... and
that's why normally, you know, you can eat even if she's pregnant.
Because even if she's pregnant, you know, then maybe you... this אפוטרופוס
apotropus solves the problem. So it's not because we're not concerned it'll
be a boy. Even if we are concerned it'll be a boy,
the אפוטרופוס apotropus solves the problem.
Okay, so what happens to the idea that before the עובר oover
is born,
the living עבדים avadim don't have 100% access to the...?
Right, so that's what it's saying. So if this עובר oover is
given out of the ten slaves, he's given these two, these two
don't eat. They're owned by the עובר oover and the עובר oover
can't cause them to eat. The other eight that are now owned
by the other brothers do eat.
Does the force of the אפוטרופוס apotropus therefore sort of takes the
עובר oover and those slaves sort of out of...?
Exactly. So as opposed to the עובר oover owning a 20% of
every slave, he just owns two out of the ten slaves and
the other eight slaves are fully owned by the other brothers and
therefore they can eat. Before the אפוטרופוס apotropus he owned 20% of
every slave.
Right. Okay, so interesting structure, business structure.
Yes. But then if the fetus is a woman...
so that... ah, so how does it work? So if the girls...
if what's left are girls, then the אפוטרופוס apotropus won't help because
then all of the slaves might be owned by the male fetus.
And what if the fetus is a girl?
Then certainly all the slaves can eat. Yeah, then they would have
to redistribute. Right. All... so that's true. This would all be done
on the assumption that it would be a boy. But at least
it would free up the other slaves. Okay, so that's obviously asserting
something in this ברייתא braita that isn't there, but it's saying that's
how we could solve it in the case of the עובר oover
and it's not because we're not concerned that it'll be born as
a... live boy. So it says, לימא דרב נחמן תנאי. Leima d'Rav
Nachman Tannai. He says so maybe, so why are the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma debated? Maybe the position of רב נחמן Rav Nachman is
debated, maybe whether you're allowed to assign this
אפוטרופוס? apotropos? It says לא. Lo. No, forget the answer we just
gave. דכולי עלמא אית להו דרב נחמן. Dekulei alma it lehu d'Rav
Nachman. Everybody could hold of רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. Forget that whole
answer. We're not talking about that special case. They didn't assign an
אפוטרופוס. apotropos. והכא בשחיישינן למיעוטא קמיפלגי. V'hacha bish'chaishinan l'miuta kamiflagi.
It's funny, it just completely reverses itself. That was an interesting idea,
but back to the simple sense. No, forget the whole idea of
assigning an אפוטרופוס. apotropos. The question is, if it's a 48% chance
that a baby boy will be born, right? Because 50% chance a
boy, and it might not be born, and it might not go
to term, so is that a concern or not?
Okay, שמעון בן יוחאי... Shimon bar Yochai... okay, so that's, so that's
the position, the last opinion רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai said if it's a, if there's only boys around, I'm not
concerned about the fetus because it might not be born as a
live boy. Forget רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. Now we get to the
more cryptic statement of רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yishmael
b'no shel Rabbi Yosi. Yes.
Is there a difference between this and like איסורא issura or, you
know, getting back to the מיעוטא miuta and the רובא, ruba, because
in כשרות Kashrut don't we actually do חושש choshesh for מיעוטא? miuta?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, so... Is that the איסורא? issura? Yeah, I mean
it's very hard. I mean, you know, תוספות Tosafot sort of has
part of that question as too, about why you're not חושש choshesh
more for מיעוטא miuta here. It's a very strange statement. But it
could also be, you know, the whole question of the status of
the unborn fetus and something that's not בפנינו befaneinu and it's, you
know... but it's very bizarre that you wouldn't be concerned for 48%.
Anyway, let's keep on going. The גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי אומר משום אביו. Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yosi omer
mishum aviv. So now רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael the son of רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi in the name of his father, הבת מאכילו הבן
אינו מאכילו. Habat ma'achilo haben eino ma'achilo. If there's daughters, she allows
the slave to eat, but sons don't allow the slave to eat.
So what does that mean? מאי שנא בן דלא מאכיל? Mai shna
ben d'lo ma'achil?
Why can the son not have the slaves eat? משום חלקו של
עובר? Mishum chelko shel ubar? Because the עובר ubar has a portion.
So what's the case over here?
We don't know yet. He basically sounds like if there's a boy
around
then the slaves can't eat and
if there's a girl around they can eat,
which is like the exact reverse of what we just said in
the name of רבי שמעון בן יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. So
that's what the גמרא Gemara says. מאי שנא בן דלא מאכיל? Mai
shna ben d'lo ma'achil? If there's a son the slaves can't eat.
משום חלקו של עובר? Mishum chelko shel ubar? Because the עובר ubar
has a portion. בת נמי לתאכל נמי חלקו של עובר? Bat nami
letichel nami chelko shel ubar? In the way all the more so
if it's a girl the slaves can't eat because the עובר ubar
has a portion, either as a girl or as a boy, certainly
as a boy, but even as a girl. So what's the story?
אמר אביי הכא בנכסים מועטים עסקינן. Amar Abaye hacha binchasim muatim askinan.
We're talking about again a special case. What's the special case? There's
a very small estate. Now, the הלכה halacha by a small estate
is the sons have a right to inherit or they do inherit,
but the daughters have a right to be fed by the estate
until they're basically get married. Okay, they're supported by the estate. No,
no, that's by any estate. But by a small estate, the point
is that the daughters, their... the cost of supporting the girls until
they get married is equal to or greater than the actual assets
of the estate. So the הלכה halacha is that the girls' rights
trump the boys' inheritance and they're going to basically be completely supported
by the estate. And even if it means not only that the
boys don't inherit, but that the boys in order to just they
have to go begging in order to put food on the table,
because the girls are entitled to be supported, the boys aren't entitled
to anything. They inherit if there's what to inherit. Okay, so because
of that, this is a special case where the girls actually have
more ownership of the estate than the boys. Okay, so now let's
see how that's going to play out in terms of the slaves.
So let's take a look. הכא בנכסים מועטים עסקינן. Hacha binchasim muatim
askinan. We're talking about a small estate.
וכגון דאיכא בן בהדי בת. Uchgon d'ika ben bahadi bat. And
the question is there is a son and there is also a
daughter. So let's take a look. So the case is הבת מאכילו.
Habat ma'achilo. If there's a daughter around, so you've got the pregnant
woman... drawn up here.
Okay, here's a boy... here's a boy. Okay,
and here's the pregnant woman. Okay. Okay, and do you also have
a girl? So if it's הבן, Haben, right? Let's start with הבן
אינו מאכילו. Haben eino ma'achilo. If it's just a boy, then the
slaves can't eat. Why? Because obviously this might be... she might be
pregnant with a boy and then they'll have an equal portion and
all of the problems. But, so that's הבן אינו מאכילו. Haben eino
ma'achilo. If there's just a son alone then the slaves can't eat
because the עובר ubar might also have a portion and there's no
girls. But if there's also a בת, bat, right? If there's also
a בת, bat, then the slaves can eat. Why? Because what's going
to happen now that there's a daughter? She's going to get the
entire estate, okay, because it's נכסים מועטים. nichasim muatim. She's entitled to
totally be supported by it. Okay, so the slaves are owned by
her. Now why doesn't this
fetus ruin it? Well, let's consider the two possibilities. Maybe he's a
boy. If he's a boy, does he affect her ownership? No. No,
not in a מועט muat case. If he's a girl, does he
affect her ownership? Well, maybe shouldn't this girl also be entitled to
a portion? So the הלכה halacha is yes, but since the reason
the girls eat is because of a rabbinic
ruling תקנה takana or whatever, the rabbis did not give those rights
to the fetus. They only gave those rights to the born girl.
Okay, so this is a case where if he's a boy and
he has a portion in the estate, he doesn't in this special
case. If it's a girl and girls have a right to be
supported by the estate, that's only once they're born. And that's why
if there's a בת, bat, if there's only a בן, ben, the
slaves can't eat. If there's a בת, bat, it all goes to
her at that moment by נכסים מועטים. nechasim muatim.
When she gets born she does, not while she's a fetus.
She doesn't ruin it for everyone else.
Correct. Okay. So it says like this. So it says: וכגון דאיכא
בן בהדי בת. ukegon de'ika ben bahadi bat. ממה נפשך, mima nafshach,
either way: אי האי דמעוברה בן הוא, i hai demeubara ben hu,
if the one she's pregnant with is a boy, לאו עדיף מהאי
דקאי, lav adif mehai deka'i, he's not better than the boy that's
already around, then in this case he isn't getting any portion of
it. אי בת היא, i bat hi, and if it's a daughter,
אמאי אכלה, amai achla, why do girls eat in this case? בתקנתא
דרבנן, betakanata derabbanan, because of a rabbinic edict. כמה דלא נפקא לעולם,
kama dela nafka le'olama, until she's actually born, לא תקינו רבנן, lo
takinu rabbanan, the rabbis didn't give her support while she's a fetus,
they gave her support once she's born. Okay, so that's a
nice חידוש. chiddush. I mean, it's reading a lot into the משנה,
mishnah, but it's a nice way that it reverses this. Okay. במאי
אוקימתא? bemai okimta? What are you saying the case is talking about?
בנכסים מועטים, benechasim muatim, a limited amount, a small estate. אימא סיפא,
eima seifa, but look at the end of the ברייתא: braita: שמא
ימצאו בזכר, shema yimatze'u bazachar, this is in the statement of רבי
שמעון בר יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, maybe the fetus would be
a male, ואין הבנות במקום הבן כלום, ve'ein habanot bemakom haben klum,
and then the boy would get it all. That was in the
statement of רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. So that
shows that we're not talking about a small estate. That's saying the
boys would get it all. אדרבה בנכסים מועטים דבנות נינהו, adaraba benechasim
muatim debanot ninhu, if it were a small estate it would all
be the girls'. So, okay, fine, סיפא אתאן לנכסים מרובים. seifa atan
lenechasim merubim. Fine, the end of רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai, that's going by a big estate, but this statement of
רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yosi,
that was talking about this special case. So the גמרא Gemara says:
ובנכסים מועטים דבנות נינהו? uvenechasim muatim debanot ninhu? If it's a small
estate, is it really the girls'? דאמר רבי אסי אמר רבי יוחנן:
de'amar Rabbi Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan: יתומים שקדמו ומכרו בנכסים מועטים מה
שמכרו מכרו. yetomim shekadmu umacharu benechasim muatim ma shemacharu macharu. So if
the orphans went ahead and sold in a small estate, the boys,
then it's a binding sale. Because it's funny, this idea that even
though the girls are entitled to be supported by it, if you
ask the question, who actually has title to the
property? So yes, the girls have a right to be supported by
it and that right might
completely exhaust the estate,
empty out the entire inheritance, but until the boys might have to
go begging for food because their right entitles them to be supported.
But right now who has title to it? But title presumably is
still the boys'. The boys own it and the girls have a
right to be supported by it. It's like a debt, and so,
but ultimately the title is the boys'. And that's why if the
boys go ahead and sell it, it's a binding sale. So how
can you say that the slaves eat by virtue of the girl
and they're the girl's slaves? They're not, they're the boy's slaves if
the girls have rights to be fed by. But ultimately they're the
boy's slaves, so this doesn't solve the problem.
If the boys sell it, aren't they still obligated with the proceeds
from the sale to feed the women?
That might be, but it still proves that the title is the
boys'.
The title isn't the girls'.
Okay. So, the גמרא Gemara says: ואלא מאי בת דקתני? ve'ela mai
bat dekatani? Fine. All right. If we concede that
point, we have to
say what does it
mean
that it says girls feed? It doesn't mean girls, it means אם.
em. It means, which is quite a bizarre read, that the mother,
the woman feeds her slaves. That even in this case of עובר
ubar or whatever, if the woman can eat her slaves can eat.
But the, אי הכי, i hachi, and then it says the son
doesn't feed, it means the father. It means that the נכסי מלוג
nichsei melog eat,
the stuff that's of the mother's estate eat, but the stuff that's
of the father's estate don't eat. היינו רבי יוסי. hainu Rabbi Yosi.
So it's just what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi said, that if there's
born children and a pregnant child, then her slaves eat and his
slaves don't eat. So אכולא דרבי יוסי קתני לה. akula deRabbi Yosi
katani lah. So the גמרא Gemara says fine, it's all an expansion
of a teaching that רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael
beno shel Rabbi Yosi said, and so it's really not different than
what his father, what we had quoted in the name of his
father originally, which is obviously either way, those are two very hard
reads of the ברייתא, braita, that son and daughter mean father and
mother. All right. That is the end of the whole slaves and
the pregnant and the status of the fetus. Moving on. Yes.
A part of this, a part of this argument was that about
males being in
the
minority?
Yeah. What percent of pregnancies though end in live birth? I'm sure
that that ultimately will still lead to less than 50% of live
boys being born.
Actually, it's still a little over 50% in most of... Really? In
most... Even including miscarriages? Oh yeah, that includes miscarriages.
Really? It depends when you start counting.
In the developed world they don't
have that many miscarriages.
All right, well the world of the time of the גמרא Gemara
wasn't yet the developed world. Yes, Dov?
Maybe we could discuss those assumptions are עובר. ubar.
Right. That's not so obvious. Right. Well that's why the גמרא Gemara
says that that is possibly what's debated, right? You know, whether מזכה
לעובר קנה או לא קנה. mezakeh le-ubar kanah o lo kanah. So
it is true that the entire סוגיא sugya basically bought into רבי
יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, both assumptions. Number one that the עובר ubar inherits
and number two that the slaves don't eat while he's yet unborn.
Now the second one seems like מפקא ארחי? mapka orchi? I don't
know, you know, that's like set, that's but but the idea that
the עובר ubar inherits is, you know, but that's why the גמרא
Gemara did quote an opposite position about that, right? About you know,
שמואל Shmuel says it is true, but there's another position about that
it isn't true and you could fundamentally debate that source. Right. The
גמרא Gemara never expanded on that issue. That's discussed elsewhere, whether מזכה
לעובר קנה mezakeh le-ubar kanah and what are, you know... here the
focus is much more on the תרומה trumah aspect, right? But yeah,
the תרומה trumah aspect builds on the assumption that the עובר ubar
gets a portion in the estate and that gets developed in a
different גמרא. Gemara. Yeah.
So in for purposes of this inheritance law the עובר ubar can
be conceptualized as an independent being.
Yes, according to the assumptions of this גמרא. Gemara. Yeah.
עובר ירך אמו ubar yerech imo is part of the mother?
Well yeah, I mean so right that does become right interesting questions
of you know to what degree עובר ירך אמו ubar yerech imo
and is an עובר ubar an entity to have to have ownership
and then what are the implications then of that in terms of
questions of like abortion, you know, can you have interesting mixes of
status there, right. So that is a very interesting question. Yes. Okay,
so now moving on. Still talking about
it starts with the עובר ubar but it gets more broadly here
and this is still with issues about eating תרומה. trumah. So let's
take a look. העובר, ha-ubar, so we've already talked about the fetus,
that the fetus is not yet, his mother can't eat on behalf
of him and the fetus again is the worst both ways, forget
the slaves for a minute. If you have a בת כהן bat
kohen married to ישראל Yisrael and then her husband dies, she goes
back to eat... the question if a woman has children, you know,
has it's the same question but it's with reverse implications based on
who the woman is and who she's married to. If she doesn't
have children she goes back to eat if she has children she's
still connected to her dead husband's house. If she doesn't have children
she goes back to her father's house, her virtual father's house. How
does that play out? If she's a בת כהן bat kohen married
to ישראל Yisrael and she has children, then she's still connected to
her her dead husband's ישראל's Yisrael house, she doesn't go back to
eating תרומה. trumah. No children, she goes back to her father כהן's
kohen house, she goes back to eating תרומה. trumah. The reverse is
true if it's a בת ישראל bat Yisrael married to a כהן.
kohen. Has children, still connected to her dead husband's house כהן, kohen,
eats תרומה. trumah. No children goes back to her father ישראל's Yisrael
house, doesn't eat תרומה. trumah. If there's a עובר, ubar, so she
is caught between the two worlds. She's not, she's connected enough to
her husband that if she is a בת כהן bat kohen married
to ישראל, Yisrael, she can't eat תרומה trumah because she's still connected
enough to her dead husband, she has a she you know she's
carrying a עובר, ubar, okay, but she's not yet totally fully connected.
So if she's a בת ישראל bat Yisrael married to a כהן,
kohen, she's not yet entitled to eat תרומה. trumah. Okay, so the
עובר ubar is in this gray zone. Enough connected that it takes
her out of her father's house and would disqualify her from eating
תרומה trumah if she was a בת כהן, bat kohen, but not
connected enough that it doesn't make her fully part of her dead
husband's house to entitle her to eat if she is a בת
ישראל bat Yisrael married to a כהן. kohen. Is that clear? This
is how it does so things. Okay, and now we're going to
look at a list of ways, a list of scenarios where this
woman is quasi-connected to her husband, enough connected so not part of
her father's house and can't eat if her father's a כהן, kohen,
but not connected enough so she can't eat if she's a ישראל
Yisrael and her husband is a כהן. kohen. So the עובר ubar
is one example. We're going to see a series of examples.
What status this woman is, right?
בוגרת? bogeret? Or... Right. And if she goes regularly, let's say she's
just married whatever...
It's not about her going to her father's house. It's conceptually. It
has nothing to do with the literal father's house. Okay. העובר והיבם.
ha-ubar ve-ha-yavam. So if she has a fetus or let's say she's
got remember the יבם, yavam, she's got a brother-in-law. Okay, so think
about that's a case of זיקה, zikah, right? So that's a case
of and let's say the brother-in-law's a כהן kohen and she's a
בת ישראל bat Yisrael or the reverse, she's a בת כהן bat
kohen and the and the brother-in-law's a ישראל. Yisrael. That's a perfect
case of this gray area. Part connected partly but not fully. Enough
out of her father's house but not enough into... to her husband's
house. Or here's another example: אירוסין. erusin. Even if there's real קידושין
kiddushin but not yet נישואין. nisu'in. So she's no longer part of
her father's house, can't eat by virtue of her father, but she's
not yet fully part of her husband's house, can't eat by virtue
of her husband. Okay, והחרש, veha-cheresh, or if it's a marriage to
a deaf-mute, which halachically is not considered to be a בר דעת,
bar da'as, somebody who is a sort
of a legal competence, thank you, and therefore it's like a דרבנן
derabbanan קידושין. kiddushin. So it also would sort of be in this
mid gray zone. ובת תשע שנים ויום אחד, u-bas tesha shanim ve-yom
echad, and nine years and a day. Now, it's not exactly clear
what the relevance of nine years and a day is; it might
refer to an act of יבום yibbum done with somebody who's nine
years and a day in the act of ביאה, bi'ah, but we'll
see that in the גמרא. Gemara. But that's somehow also considered this
gray zone. In all these cases פוסלים, poslin, they invalidate her. If
she is a בת כהן bas kohen and this is a relationship
to a ישראל, yisrael, it's enough of a relationship that it invalidates
her, takes her out of her father's house. ולא מאכילים, ve-lo ma'achilin,
but it's not strong enough, so if the man is a כהן
kohen and she's a בת ישראל, bas yisrael, it's not a strong
enough relationship to allow her to eat. It's this gray zone. Now,
ספק בן תשע שנים ויום אחד ספק אינו, safek ben tesha shanim
ve-yom echad safek eino, if it's the same would be true even
if it's a ספק safek whether he's nine years and a day.
We haven't really explained what the nine-year case is. ספק הביא שתי
שערות ספק לא הביא, safek hevi shtei searos safek lo hevi, or
in the case of let's say כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, אירוסין. erusin.
Let's say he is a questionable adult. We don't know if he
has two pubic hairs or, you know, if he's thirteen years old,
presumably we know if he's thirteen years old. So we don't know
if he's a halachic adult and he does קידושין kiddushin with this
woman. So why don't we say, "Oh, it's only a ספק safek
קידושין, kiddushin, she should still continue eating if she's a בת כהן."
bas kohen. No, even though it's only a ספק, safek, and it's
a ספק safek of this status, that's enough to invalidate her from
eating. Now, here's another scenario not related to the above, but it's
also a question of a ספק. safek. נפלה הבית עליו ועל בת
אחיו. nafal habayis alav ve-al bas achiv. Okay, now we're getting back
to a classic יבום yibbum case. Okay, he is married to his
niece. All right, and no kids. It's going to be a יבום
yibbum case. And a house collapsed on him and his wife, who
happens to be his niece. Now, if he happens to also have
another co-wife, a צרה, tzarah, remember all these fun cases? So, is
his brother, father of his wife, is his brother has a מצוה
mitzvah of יבום yibbum to the surviving co-wife? So it depends of
the order of death. If first his wife died and then he
died, so then when he died he left behind just one wife,
the surviving co-wife, and his brother has a מצוה mitzvah of יבום.
yibbum. But if the order of death was the reverse, first he
died, then he left behind two wives, one of which was his
brother's daughter, and therefore the co-wife is out of the picture, right?
There's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibbum. So what's the story? נפלה
הבית עליו ועל בת אחיו ואין ידוע איזה מהן מת ראשון צרתה
חולצת ולא מתייבמת. nafal habayis alav ve-al bas achiv ve-ein yadu'a eizeh
mei-hen mes rishon tzarosah choletzes ve-lo misyabbemes. So the co-wife does חליצה,
chalitzah, not יבום yibbum because we don't know if you could do
יבום. yibbum. Okay, that was a complete throwback. What? Well, no, רש"י
Rashi says it's in the משנה Mishna because we're talking about we
mentioned יבם yavam and we're talking about ספק safek cases, it was
really a total digression. Okay, now גמרא: Gemara: עובר, ubar, אי בת
כהן לישראל היא, ei bas kohen le-yisrael hi, if it's a כהן
kohen woman married to a ישראל, yisrael,
he פוסלה, paslah, then the עובר ubar invalidates. כשחזרה, ke-she-chazarah, that she
goes back to her father's house, כנעוריה, ki-ne'ureha, when it's like her
youth, פרט למעוברת, perat le-me'uberes, to exclude a case of pregnant is
not enough reverting to her original state. If she's still pregnant, she's
still somewhat connected, and therefore she can't go back to eating תרומה
terumah like she used to. אי בת ישראל לכהן היא, ei bas
yisrael le-kohen hi, and if she's a בת ישראל bas yisrael married
to a
כהן, kohen, היא לא מאכיל, hi lo ma'achil, then the relationship is
not strong enough to let her eat,
because ילוד מאכיל שאין ילוד מאכיל, yalud ma'achil she-ein yalud ma'achil, only
a as we were talking about before, a born child can entitle
the slaves or the mother to eat, an unborn child is not
yet enough. It doesn't quite פוסל, posel, but that's what we're asserting.
Okay, so that's the gray zone. היבם, ha-yavam, a brother-in-law, אי
בת כהן לישראל היא, ei bas kohen le-yisrael hi, if it's a
בת כהן bas kohen and this brother-in-law's a ישראל, yisrael, פוסלה, paslah,
he invalidates her. ושבה אל בית אביה, ve-shavah el beis aviha, she
can return because when does she go back to eating תרומה? terumah?
When she returns to her father's house. פרט לשומרת יבם, perat le-shomeres
yavam, she can't return yet, she's still bound up, she needs חליצה
chalitzah to free her. אי בת ישראל לכהן היא, ei bas yisrael
le-kohen hi, and if he's a כהן kohen and she's a בת
ישראל, bas yisrael, לא מאכיל לה, lo ma'achil lah, he doesn't eat
her, because קנין כספו אמר רחמנא, kinyan kaspo amar rachamana, it'd have
to be like his acquisition of money, there we go back to
woman being a קנין, kinyan, והאי קנין דאחיו הוא, ve-hai kinyan de-achiv
hu, and this isn't woman he married, it's a woman his brother
married. Now, of course once he does יבום, yibbum, then it'll be
fully like his wife, but at this stage it's not enough of
a relationship. Okay, ואירוסין, ve-eirusin, it's almost a קל וחומר kal va-chomer
from the case of אירוסין eirusin where you actually did קידושין kiddushin
and not נישואין, nisu'in, that's not enough. So let's see why.
אי בת כהן ei bas kohen now the guy
isn't dead. אם בת כהן לישראל היא im bat kohen l'Yisrael hee
פסלה pasla then he invalidates her because it says right that it's
because the פסוק pasuk says ובת כהן כי תהיה לאיש זר u'bat
kohen ki tihyeh l'ish zar if she belongs to you know again
that קנין kinyan idea or is to another man so once there's
some קנין kinyan she's no longer in her father's house again although
interestingly because the whole idea of נישואין nissuin conceptually is leaving the
father's house and going right to the to the groom's house to
the husband's house conceptually she's in the father's house after אירוסין erusin
until נישואין nissuin so you could say oh she's in the father's
house but no that connection to that other man that's enough to
to make it not fully seen as her father's house and it's
or even if she's her father's house she's also to another man
if you want to put it that way and therefore therefore she
no longer eats based on her father's house ואי בת ישראל לכהן
היא v'ee bat Yisrael l'kohen hee and if a בת ישראל bat
Yisrael married to a כהן kohen so לא מאכילה משום דעולא lo
machila mishum d'Ula now here's an interesting question why is קידושין kiddushin
not enough to let a woman eat תרומה terumah if it's קידושין
kiddushin to a כהן kohen so this is a מחלוקת machlokes בבלי
Bavli ירושלמי Yerushalmi right the
בבלי Bavli says that the reason a woman married to a כהן
kohen eats תרומה terumah it says
קנין כספו הוא יאכל בלחמו kinyan kaspo hu yochal belachmo his acquisition
of money can eat so the גמרא gemara says acquisition of money
is slaves and wife because you do קידושין kiddushin with money and
again that קנין kinyan idea so in principle after קידושין kiddushin before
נישואין nissuin a woman married to a כהן kohen actually could eat
but there's עולא Ulla's statement עולא Ulla says in practice though where's
this woman living during the period of קידושין kiddushin before נישואין nissuin
in her father's house what's going to happen if the כהן kohen
sends her תרומה terumah she's going to wind up sharing it with
her father and her brother and so on so it's a rabbinic
concern so according to actually the בבלי Bavli הלכתית halachikly she actually
can eat at this stage the ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually says no she
doesn't eat by virtue of קנין כספו kinyan kaspo she eats by
issue of ביתו הם יאכלו בלחמו beito hem yochlu belachmo and the
idea of ביתו beito household is only after
נישואין nissuin so actually the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says that it's actually biblical
that she does not eat until נישואין nissuin which is consistent with
these ideas that this is a gray zone you know and it's
not rabbinic it really is lives in both worlds okay so that's
that
just what was עולא Ulla he said all
that עולא Ulla no עולא Ulla didn't say the ירושלמי Yerushalmi עולא
Ulla said because we're afraid she'll feed her father and brother okay
והחרש v'hacheresh if it's a deaf mute so again this is a
whole important area of הלכה halacha about how the whole status of
חרש cheresh changed once they created these schools for the deaf and
so on and realized you know they were intelligent but at this
stage anyway they're treated as not competent so אי בת כהן לישראל
היא ee bat kohen l'Yisrael hee if she's a בת כהן bat
kohen married to ישראל Yisrael פסלה דקנייה בתקנתא דרבנן pasla d'kanya bitakanas
d'rabanan because the rabbis recognized that even if a חרש cheresh was
not seen as sort of fully competent he was certainly at a
higher level than let's say a שוטה shota who was somebody that
really had no you know was like insane or whatever or you
know or somebody who had like very very low intelligence and therefore
a חרש cheresh at least rabbinically had a rabbinic institution of marriage
so that rabbinic institution was enough to remove her from her father's
house ואי בת ישראל לכהן היא v'ee bat Yisrael l'kohen hee and
obviously if she's a בת ישראל bat Yisrael married to a כהן
kohen the rabbinic institution isn't going to be enough to entitle her
to eat so קנין כספו אמר רחמנא והאי לאו בר קנין הוא
kinyan kaspo amar rachmana v'hai lav bar kinyan hu it has to
really be again again the acquisition and this is something that biblically
it is not a קידושין kiddushin so clearly she cannot eat based
on that now we get to let's just get a little further
now we get to the בן תשע שנים ויום אחד ben tishah
shanim v'yom echad which is the one that was less clear what
the case was it's
קידושין kiddushin and acquisition yes because it's only rabbinic what which is
rabbinic the
חרש cheresh's ability to do קידושין kiddushin is only rabbinic
oh i see
okay so biblically it's not a קידושין kiddushin
but rabbinically it's a marriage
rabbinically but not biblically so rabbinically it's enough to invalidate her from
her father's house but because it's not biblical it's not enough to
entitle her to eat if he's a כהן kohen okay ובן
תשע שנים u'ven tishah shanim nine years old קא סלקא דעתך בשומרת
יבם ובן תשע שנים ויום אחד ka salka daitach b'shomeres yavam u'ven
tishah shanim v'yom echad right because תשע שנים tishah shanim is normally
about sex that that's considered an act of sex so the relevant
case would be that she was a woman waiting for יבום yibbum
the brother-in-law was nine years old and a day could be an
act of sex and he went and had sex with her so
okay what's the problem it's יבום yibbum so let's take a look
so רמי remai אי למפסל ee l'mifsal is it to say that
she is invalidated
meaning קטן נמי פסל katan nami pasal meaning that the fact that
she is a בת כהן bat kohen and she can't eat because
of her connection to this boy so even if he was less
than nine years old she right if she here is even if
the brother is
a
three year old or
a one year old right she's still a שומרת יבם shomeres yavam
forget whether he's had sex with her, not had sex with her,
whatever, if he's one day old, he prevents her from going back
to her father's house, she's still bound up until there's either חליצה
chalitzah or יבום. yibum. So even even less than nine years old.
אי הכי? ei hachi? So the point is no, that whether he's
entitled to have her eat on his behalf. So גדול נמי לא
מאכיל gadol nami lo ma'achil before sex has been done, the גמרא
Gemara is assuming we haven't had sex yet. So even as an
adult she can't eat yet until they consummate. So אמר אביי amar
Abaye הכא ביבם בן תשע שנים ויום אחד הבא על יבמתו עסקינן.
hacha biyavam ben tesha shanim veyom echad haba al yevamto askinan. No,
no, no, we're talking about that they had sex, okay? And here's
the חידוש: chiddush: דמדאורייתא קני ליה, demide'oraita kani lei,
biblically, it's a good act of יבום. yibum. So so now that
he's that they've had sex, and this boy is a כהן, kohen,
she should be entitled to eat. סלקא דעתך אמינא הואיל ומדאורייתא קני
ליה בביאתו ביאה, salka daitach amina ho'il umide'oraita kani lei bevi'ato bi'ah,
since this sex is sex, אימא תיכול, eima tichol, and so he's
a כהן, kohen, she should be allowed to eat. קא משמע לן
עשו ביאת בן תשע שנים ויום אחד כמאמר בגדול. ka mashma lan
asu bi'at ben tesha shanim veyom echad kemamar begadol. Yes,
biblically you're right. But rabbinically, even though this act of sex is
a complete act of יבום, yibum, rabbinically we look at it as
only מאמר, ma'amar, as though that the יבום yibum has not been
completed, and it's a stronger relationship but it's not yet a full
relationship. And therefore that's a nice read of the משנה. Mishnah. Nine
years old and a day, they've had sex, you might think she's
entitled to eat? No, rabbinically this is still in the gray zone
and she's not entitled to eat.
He's too young.
Okay, אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, that's a nice read. You
know what רבא Rava says? אי הכי, ei hachi, סיפא דקתני ספק
בן תשע שנים ויום
אחד ספק שאינו,
seifa diktani safek ben tesha shanim veyom
echad safek she'eino, the משנה Mishnah even says this is true even
if he's not necessarily, if it's doubtful if he's nine years old.
So רבא Rava says, I don't get it, השתא ודאי בן תשע
לא מאכיל, hashta vadai ben tesha lo ma'achil, of course she can't
eat if if he's definitely nine years old and it's definitely an
act of sex biblically and she still can't eat. ספק מיבעיא? safek
mibaya? Of course if he might be younger it's not going to
work. Okay, so the end of the משנה Mishnah wouldn't work according
to you. The end of the משנה Mishnah sounds like that if
he were definitely younger it would be better. According to this if
he's definitely younger it would even be worse. אלא אמר רבא, ela
amar Rava, בבן תשע שנים ויום אחד דהנך פסולין תני. beven tesha
shanim veyom echad dahanach pesulin tani.
We're not talking about יבום yibum anymore, we're talking about people that
are actually invalidate the woman. And this is going to be the
next משנה, Mishnah, remember this is another theme we keep on going
back to, that if there is basically somebody, a ממזר, mamzer, a
נתין, netin, you know, any type of person whose act of sex
is forbidden, even a לאו, lav, not a כרת, karet, and has
sex with her, with this woman, she now becomes like a חללה
chalalah or זונה zonah depending on the case, and now can no
longer marry a כהן, kohen, and if she was a בת כהן
bat kohen also can no longer eat תרומה terumah once she's had
this forbidden act of sex. So רבא Rava says, that's the case.
We're talking about she's had sex with somebody that she's that is
she's forbidden to and that would actually change her status. So once
he's nine years and a day, that invalidates her. Okay, not it's
not really a gray zone, it really completely invalidates her. Okay, so
let's take a look.
It means it so it can be a
ביאת גדול bi'at gadol then. It's not כי ki ביאת גדול, bi'at
gadol, it's ביאת גדול. bi'at gadol. בבן תשע שנים ויום אחד דהנך
פסולין תני, beven tesha shanim veyom echad dahanach pesulin tani, the פסול
pasul people, דפסלי בביאתן, deposli bevi'atan, וכדתניא, uchid'tanya, they invalidate like we
taught in the ברייתא, Baraita, בן תשע שנים ויום אחד ben tesha
shanim veyom echad there, it's all these following pieces. גר עמוני ומואבי,
ger Amoni uMo'avi, if it's a convert who is an Ammonite or
a Moabite, right, who you're not allowed to who you know, לא
יבא עמוני בקהל השם lo yavo Amoni bikhal Hashem etc, or so
there's a negative prohibition of having them marry even if they convert.
מצרי ואדומי, Mitzri ve'Edomi, or a מצרי Mitzri or an אדומי Edomi
with the before the third generation, כותי נתין חלל וממזר, Kuti, Netin,
Chalal, uMamzer, or a Samaritan and a נתין Netin assuming that these
people are not fully Jews, we won't get into that right now,
חלל, Chalal, so a כהן kohen who is a חלל chalal makes
a woman a חללה chalalah with his act of sex, or a
ממזר, mamzer, so all of these people are forbidden acts of sex
or a חלל chalal is not a forbidden act of sex but
it makes the woman a חללה. chalalah. Anyway, and all these cases
שבא על כהנת לוויה וישראלית sheba al kohenet, Leviyah veYisre'elit had sex
with either a woman whether she's a בת כהן bat kohen or
or just a normal ישראלית, Yisre'elit, פסלוה, pasluha, invalidate her. So if
it's a בת כהן, bat kohen, prevent her from eating תרומה, terumah,
and if it's a ישראלית, Yisre'elit, prevent her from marrying a כהן.
kohen. Okay, so he says, although the first cases in the משנה
Mishnah were all these cases of being in this gray zone, partly
connected to the husband, partly not, and therefore not eating, now we're
talking about a different issue. The reason she doesn't eat is no
gray zone, is that she's had sex and it's invalidated her. But
the point is, even though the kid was only nine years old.
And now we understand, even if it's only a ספק safek if
he was nine years old, she still is invalidated even on the
basis of the ספק. safek. Okay, והא, veha, so that's that's his
read of the משנה, Mishnah, which the גמרא Gemara keeps to. והא
מדקתני סיפא, veha midiktani seifa, the end of the משנה, Mishnah, not
the משנה Mishnah we read now, the משנה... Mishnah... but the משנה
mishna we’re going to read that follows this, which is seen as
the end of our משנה, mishna, the end of the משנה mishna
says: ואם אינם ראוים לבוא בישראל הרי אלו פוסלין. v’im einam rauyin
lavo b’Yisrael harei elu poslin.
If she
had sex with people that are not able to be part of
the to marry with Jews, they invalidate her. So that’s going to
be the following משנה’s mishna going to talk about sex with somebody
that she’s not allowed to have sex with. מכלל דרישא לאו בפסולין
עסקינן, mikh’lal d’reisha lav bif’sulin askinan, so you see that we’re talking
here not yet in the case of people that are to the
people invalid people of having sex with. So גמרא gemara says: no,
there the two categories. רישא פסולי קהל, reisha p’sulei kahal, here we’re
talking about people that are not allowed to marry not only not
only כהונה kehuna problems, not allowed to marry even a even with
a ישראל, Yisrael, right, Ammonite, Moabite, מצרי, Mitzri, ממזר, mamzer, it’s not
about כהונה. kehuna. That’s one category of forbidden sexual acts and סיפא
seifa the next משנה mishna it’s going to talk about forbidden sexual
acts is the פסולי כהונה, p’sulei kehuna, people that are unique
to כהנים, kohanim, גרושה לכהן, grusha l’kohen, אלמנה לכהן, almana l’kohen, not
necessarily because on the one hand if it’s because more כהונה kehuna
specific it might have more implications for כהונה. kehuna. If it’s more
general then it might be just seen as more weighty. Okay, so
the end is and this points us to what the next משנה’s
mishna going to be about is not this interesting gray zone partly
connected to her father’s house partly to her husband, it’s just about
sex with forbidden forbidden acts of sex makes this woman
אסורה לכהן asura l’kohen and again make her חללה chalala or make
her זונה zona or whatever in one of those categories and also
make her unable to eat תרומה. teruma. And now we’re going to
turn our attention exactly to those issues. So let’s take a look.
גופא. gufa. בן תשע שנים ויום אחד. ben taysha shanim v’yom echad.
Okay, nine years and a day, whether he is a גר, ger,
עמוני, Ammoni, או מואבי, o Moavi, whether he’s a convert of an
Ammonite or Moabite, מצרי, Mitzri, אדומי, Edomi, כותי, Kuti, נתין, Natin, חלל,
chalal, וממזר, u’mamzer, שבא על כהנת לויים וישראלית פסלה. she’ba al kohenet
Levi’im v’Yisraelit pasla. Okay, that’s what we quoted. Now we get the
end of it. Right, רבי רבי יוסי
אומר, Rabbi Rabbi Yossi omer, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says, כל שזרעו
פסול פוסל. kol she’zar’o pasul posel. Now by the way I know
Dov you like this as the difference between גופא gufa and אמר
מר. amar mar. So גופא gufa is we’re going back to what
we quoted and we’re quoting it in full. So here you see
exactly that. The first line we already quoted, but now we’re quoting
the end of the ברייתא. braita. רבי יוסי אומר כל שזרעו פסול
פוסל.
Rabbi Yossi omer
kol she’zar’o pasul posel. Anybody whose children is invalid will invalidate this
woman through this act of sex. וכל שאין זרעו פסול אינו פוסל.
v’kol she’ein zar’o pasul eino posel. Anybody whose child is not
invalid will not invalidate the woman. So what type of a person
is forbidden to have sex with but the child is not forbidden?
Can you think about that? Yes to the yes. What what person
is it invalid to have sex with but the child is not
problematic? Something like
she already belongs to someone else.
What do you mean belongs? Like she’s married to someone
or oh you mean forbidden because she’s a married woman or something
like that. Oh okay but we’re talking here about the man, that’s
true about a woman you would have that. So what about somebody
who’s only forbidden up to three generations and you’re dealing with the
third generation? Oh.
So he’s right on the cusp of going into right. Anyway we’ll
see about we’ll see about what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi means but
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says it’s only when the child would be
invalid that he invalidates the woman. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel omer, כל שאתה נושא בתו אתה נושא אלמנתו. kol
she’ata nosei bito ata nosei almanato.
Anybody who you could marry his daughter you could marry his widow
the woman he had sex with. וכל שאי אתה נושא בתו אי
אתה נושא אלמנתו. v’kol she’ei ata nosei bito ei ata nosei almanato.
If you couldn’t marry his daughter you can’t you the כהן kohen
meaning cannot marry his widow, it doesn’t invalidate the woman. Sounds very
much like the previous point, right? About what about what’s the status
of the child depends on determines the status of the woman. We’ll
see about that in the גמרא. gemara. Okay מנא הני מילי. m’na
hanei mili. Let’s get started. Where do you know this idea? This
basic idea that sex with a man that you’re not allowed to
have sex with if a woman has sex with such a man
that’s biblically forbidden even if it’s a simple forbidden of a לאו
lav that it invalidates her to marry a כהן kohen and if
she’s a כהנת kohenet it invalidates her to eat תרומה. teruma. מנא
הני מילי. m’na hanei mili. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אמר קרא,
amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says: ובת
כהן כי תהיה לאיש זר. u’vat kohen ki tihye l’ish zar.
Now the simple sense of the פסוק pasuk is she’s married to
a foreign man means a non-כהן kohen and once she’s married to
a non-כהן kohen she can no longer eat the תרומה teruma of
her father’s house. Okay, but we’re going to read it the following
way. כיון שנבעלה לפסול לה, keivan she’niv’ala l’pasul lah, זר zar means
somebody that’s totally foreign, it’s somebody you shouldn't be having sex with,
somebody who is forbidden to you. Once she has sex with somebody
that is forbidden to her פסלה pasla she is invalidated for eating
תרומה. teruma. So as opposed to just during the period you’re married
to a non-כהן kohen don’t eat תרומה teruma and if he dies
you go back and you eat תרומה, teruma, that’s the פשט, pshat,
we’re saying if you ever have sex with a full זר zar
somebody who you’re never you’re forbidden to you’re completely invalidated from ever
eating תרומה teruma in the future. Okay so that doesn’t tell about
being אסור asur to marry a כהן kohen but it invalidates her
תרומה. teruma. So the גמרא gemara says: האי מיבעי ליה, hai mibei
lei, but one minute we need this for the פשט. pshat. דקאמר
רחמנא בת כהן דאינסבא לזר לא תאכל, d’ka’amar Rachmana bat kohen d’ins’va
l’zar lo tochal, a בת כהן bat kohen who’s married to a
non-כהן kohen can’t eat תרומה, teruma, you need it for the פשט.
pshat. But it says no, that we could have figured out somewhere
else. ההיא משבה בית אביה כנעוריה מלחם אביה תאכל, Hahi mishavah beit
aviha kine'ureha milechem aviha tochal, no, we should have figured that out
from later, where it says that if the guy dies, then she
can go back and eat in the the תרומה Terumah from her
father's house. So implicitly we can figure out that while she's married
she can't. Gemara says לא דוקא, la davka, we can learn it
מדהקאמר רחמנא ושבה אל בית אביה תאכל מכלל דעד השתא לא אכלה.
mideka'amar rachmana v'shavah el beit aviha tochal michlal d'ad hashta lo achla.
So we could have figured it out from the end. So here
where it says כי תהיה, ki tihyeh, she cannot eat, that's a
separate issue. Gemara says no, אם מההיא, im mehahi, had I just
inferred it from after the husband dies she can go back, הוה
אמינא לאו הבא מכלל עשה עשה, hava amina lav haba michlal aseh
aseh, that okay, from there I can infer she's not allowed while
she's married, but that's only a negative idea, don't eat while you're
married, that's inferred from a positive, after he dies, go back, okay?
And it only has the weight of a positive מצוה. mitzvah. I
need the תורה Torah to black and white say it's a negative
prohibition and it's forbidden. כתב רחמנא האי ללאו, Katav rachmana hai l'lav,
the תורה Torah had to say when she's married to a non-כהן,
kohen, don't eat, to make it a real negative prohibition, not to
tell you this new idea of sex with a man she's forbidden
to. Gemara says no, we could have learned out the negative prohibition
from another פסוק pasuk of while she's married to a non-כהן. kohen.
לאו, Lav, the negative prohibition we learn out from וכל זר לא
יאכל קדש. v'chol zar lo yochal kodesh. Any non-כהן kohen can't eat
קדש, kodesh, תרומה, Terumah, so rather
than learning it as the פשט, pshat, if you're a non-כהן kohen
you can't eat תרומה, Terumah, we mean if you're connected to a
non-כהן kohen you can't eat תרומה. Terumah. And then again, כי תהיה
לאיש זר ki tihyeh l'ish zar refers to sex with a man
she's forbidden to. Gemara says נפקא, nafka, that's how we learn
it from. Gemara says one minute, ההוא, hahu, top of 68 עמוד
ב'. 68 amud bais. ההוא מיבעי ליה לגופיה, Hahu miba'ei lei l'gufeh,
we need that for itself to tell you, if you're a non-כהן,
kohen, you can't eat תרומה. Terumah. לא תרי וכל זר כתיבי, La
trei v'chol zar ktivi, it says twice וכל זר לא יאכל קדש.
v'chol zar lo yochal kodesh. רש"י Rashi quotes it, second line of
רש"י, Rashi, וכל זר לא יאכל קדש, v'chol zar lo yochal kodesh,
ואידך בבת כהן כתיב ושבה אל בית אביה מלחם אביה תאכל וכל
זר לא יאכל בו. v'idach b'vat kohen ktiv v'shavah el beit aviha
milechem aviha tochal v'chol zar lo yochal bo. Okay?
So there's two וכל זר. v'chol zar. One is that a non-כהן
kohen can't eat, and the other is a woman married to a
non-כהן kohen can't eat. And כי תהיה לאיש זר ki tihyeh l'ish
zar is about sex with a man she's forbidden to. Exactly.
ואכתי מיבעי ליה לכדרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, V'kati miba'ei lei l'chiderabbi Yose
birabbi Chanina,
one minute, we still need כי תהיה לאיש זר ki tihyeh l'ish
zar not to tell me sex with a man you're forbidden to,
but to tell you what Rabbi Yose birabbi Chanina says. דאמר רבי
יוסי ברבי חנינא וכל זר זרות אמרתי לך וכל זר לא יאכל
בו,
D'amar Rabbi Yose birabbi Chanina v'chol zar
zarut amarti lach v'chol zar lo yochal bo, excuse me, it can't
tell you married to a non-כהן, kohen, it has to tell you
something else. וכל זר זרות אמרתי לך ולא אנינות. v'chol zar zarut
amarti l'cha v'lo aninut.
Only being a זר zar is forbidden to eat תרומה, Terumah, an
אונן onen is not. An אונן onen is forbidden to eat קרבנות
korbanot but not forbidden to eat תרומה. Terumah. So that's what you
need it
for, not to tell you married to a
non-כהן. kohen. לכדרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא מוכל זר נפקא. Lichiderabbi Yose birabbi
Chanina m'v'chol zar nafka. No, no, that's from the word וכל. v'chol.
וכל v'chol comes to tell you only about being a זר, zar,
not about something else, although normally וכל v'chol would seem to be
more expansive. And anyway,
זר zar is coming to tell you married to a non-כהן. kohen.
So we have one וכל זר לא יאכל בו v'chol zar lo
yochal bo to tell you a non-כהן kohen can't eat. The other
זר לא יאכל zar lo yochal tells you married to a non-כהן
kohen you can't eat. And וכל v'chol tells only זרות zarut not
אנינות. aninut. And then we're left with the פסוק pasuk of כי
תהיה לאיש זר ki tihyeh l'ish zar to tell you that sex
with a man she's forbidden to invalidates her.
Gemara's not done.
ואכתי מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, v'achti miba'ei lei l'chidetanya, כשהיא חוזרת חוזרת לתרומה
ואינה חוזרת לחזה ושוק, kishehi chozeret chozeret l'trumah v'eina chozeret l'chazeh v'shok,
okay, that when a woman, her husband dies and she goes back
to eating תרומה, Terumah, she goes back to eating תרומה, Terumah, she
does not go back to eating חזה ושוק chazeh v'shok which is
interesting. ואמר רמי בר אבין אמר רב אשי מאי קרא, v'amar Rami
bar Avin amar Rav Ashi mai kra, where do you know this
from? Where's the verse? דכתיב ובת כהן כי תהיה לאיש זר היא
בתרומת הקדשים לא תאכל. d'chtiv u'vat kohen ki tihyeh l'ish zar hi
bi'trumat hakodashim lo teichol. That when she is married to this man,
she cannot eat the תרומה, Terumah, but the phrase of תרומה Terumah
is תרומת הקדשים. trumat hakodashim. And the way we're going to read
it is לא תאכל במורם מן הקדשים. lo teichol b'muram min hakodashim.
תרומת הקדשים trumat hakodashim doesn't mean תרומה, Terumah, it means the חזה
ושוק chazeh v'shok which is lifted up from קרבנות. korbanot. So once
she was married to a non-כהן, kohen, not during the marriage, during
the marriage she can't eat תרומה Terumah and after she can, but
the other way we're reading the פסוק pasuk is that once she
had been married to him, she can no longer from that point
on, even after he dies, go back to eating the קדשים. kodshim.
So again, it's not
telling you sex with a man she's forbidden to, it's telling you
this special הלכה halacha that she never goes back to eating קדשים.
kodshim. No, אם כן נכתוב קרא היא בקדשים לא תאכל. im kein
niktav kra hi b'kodashim lo teichol. Then just if all it wanted
to say was don't eat קדשים kodshim after you've been married to
a non-כהן, kohen, just say קדשים. kodshim. מאי בתרומת הקדשים, mai bi'trumat
hakodashim, why does it also use the word תרומה? Terumah? שמע מינה
תרתי, shma mina tarti, to tell you both. So it's a very
complicated thing, but the point is we've got enough פסוקים psukim to
tell me a non-כהן kohen can't eat, married to a non-כהן kohen
can't eat, that after her husband dies she goes back to תרומה
Terumah but she doesn't go back
to
קרבנות. korbanot.
Yeah, this, this wouldn't be קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim because that's only
male, but would this be the מתנות כהנים? Matenot Kohanim? Yeah. Okay.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, right, because obviously she can eat שלמים. Shelamim. Right, this is
something that specifically, right, is eaten by, right.
Okay. So גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay. Now, כהנת, Kohenes, we find that a כהנת Kohenes becomes invalidated
of eating תרומה. Terumah. But לויה Leviyah and ישראלית Yisraelis מנין? minayin?
And that's not just a question of women who are לויה Leviyah
and ישראלית, Yisraelis, it's a question of the other הלכה. halachah. One
הלכה halachah is she stops eating תרומה. Terumah. Fine. Quoted a פסוק
pasuk about eating תרומה. Terumah. How do you know she becomes forbidden
to marry a כהן? Kohen? Okay, and that's obviously the much more
relevant הלכה halachah for us nowadays. So that's what's applicable to a
לויה Leviyah and ישראלית, Yisraelis, they never eat תרומה. Terumah. But how
do you know this other הלכה halachah that applies to no matter
whether the woman is a בת כהן bas Kohen or לויה Leviyah
and ישראלית Yisraelis that she's forbidden to marry a
כהן Kohen if
she has sex with somebody she's forbidden to? Since דאמר רבי אבא
אמר רב de-amar Rebbe Abba amar Rav בת ובת, bas u-bas, הכא
נמי hacha nami בת ובת, bas u-bas, because the פסוק pasuk says
ובת כהן כי תהיה לאיש זר, u-bas Kohen ki tihiyeh le-ish zar,
so the extra ו vav ובת u-bas somehow is coming to tell
me that not only is this a הלכה halachah for תרומה, Terumah,
or let me say it this way, not only is it a
הלכה halachah for a בת כהן, bas Kohen, it's a הלכה halachah
for all women, ובת, u-bas, all women, even a לויה Leviyah and
ישראלית. Yisraelis. Once it's a הלכה halachah for לויות Leviyis and ישראליות,
Yisraeliyos, the only relevant can't be a תרומה Terumah relevance, it has
to be a marriage to a כהן Kohen relevance. So the גמרא
Gemara says כמאן? keman? כרבי עקיבא דדרש ווים? ke-Rebbe Akiva de-darish vavim?
Is this going like רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva that learns out something
from an extra ו? vav? No, אפילו תימא רבנן, afilu tema rabanan,
even the rabbis who normally don't learn out an extra ו, vav,
כולי ובת קרא יתירה הוא. kulei u-bas kra yeseira hu. The whole
ובת u-bas is extra because it just could have said כי תהיה
לאיש זר. ki tihiyeh le-ish zar. Why did it have to say
ובת כהן? u-bas Kohen? Whose phone is that? Anyway, why did it
have to say ובת כהן? u-bas Kohen? So that whole thing is
extra and therefore that's telling you it applies even to a non
בת כהן, bas Kohen, even to ישראלית Yisraelis and לויה. Leviyah. And
if it applies to לויה Leviyah and ישראלית, Yisraelis, it applies not
only to תרומה Terumah but even to marriage. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אשכחן לתרומה לכהונה מנלן? ashchan li-Terumah li-khuna
minalan?
So we now know that they can't eat תרומה. Terumah. How do
you know they can't marry a כהן? Kohen? So it says, like
I've been telling you, אטו לויה וישראלית לאו לכהונה מפקינן להו? atu
Leviyah ve-Yisraelis lav li-khuna ma-p'ki-nan le-hu? I don't understand. When we said
it's talking about a ישראלית Yisraelis and a לויה, Leviyah, obviously that
means for the purpose of not marrying a כהן. Kohen. דאי לתרומה,
de-ee li-Terumah, because if it was about not eating תרומה, Terumah, what,
בנות מיכלא תרומה נינהו? benoseiy-ma-khala Terumah ninhu? Could they eat תרומה Terumah
to begin with? So the גמרא, Gemara, let's just read one more
line. אלמה לא, alama lo, why not? I can tell you how
ישראלית Yisraelis could have eaten תרומה. Terumah. משכחת לה דאכלה בשביל בנה.
mishkachas la de-kachlah bishvil benah.
Let's say her son was, let's say she had been married to
a כהן, Kohen, she had a son, she was eating תרומה Terumah
because of her son and now she had sex with this man
she's forbidden to, right? So there could be a case of that
it's still in the world of תרומה Terumah and it's relevant to
a ישראלית Yisraelis because she has a son with a כהן Kohen
and because now she's had this forbidden sex, now she's invalidated. So
we're not yet in the world of marrying כהנים, Kohanim, maybe we're
just still in the world of תרומה. Terumah. So the גמרא Gemara
says wait a minute. בנה, benah, בשביל בנה... bishvil benah...
so the גמרא Gemara says בשביל בנה קל
וחומר? bishvil benah kal va-chomer? No, I wouldn't need a פסוק pasuk
to tell me that. That's a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. ומה כהנת
דבקדשה דנפשה אכלה, u-mah kohenes di-bi-kdusha di-nafshah achlah, a
בת כהן bas Kohen that could eat on her own account, פסלה,
paslah, this act of sex invalidates her. לויה וישראלית דלא אכלה אלא
בשביל בנה, Leviyah ve-Yisraelis de-lo achlah ela bishvil benah, this case where
she's only eating because of her child, לא כל שכן, lo kol
she-ken, of course
forbidden sex would invalidate her.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, that's not a קל וחומר. kal
va-chomer. מה לכהנת? mah le-kohenes? That it makes a lot of sense.
כהנת דקדיש גופה, kohenes de-kadesh gufah, a בת כהן bas Kohen that's
eating because of her personal status, then
פסלה, paslah, sex impinges on her personal status and invalidates her. הא,
ha, this בת ישראל bas Yisrael that's only דלא קדיש גופה, de-lo
kadesh gufah, she's not, doesn't have קדושה, kedushah, it's not her status
that entitles her to eat, it's her child that entitles her to
eat. So maybe her status doesn't matter, maybe her status is irrelevant.
If she's a ישראלית Yisraelis and she can eat, maybe even if
she had forbidden sex she can eat, it's not about her status.
לא פסלה. lo paslah.
So therefore, so we're going to end with this question, so now
we said we've included
ישראלית, Yisraelis, כהנת, Kohenes, and לויה Leviyah that forbidden sex invalidates them
for eating תרומה Terumah and you need to include even ישראלית Yisraelis
and לויה Leviyah that they can't eat תרומה Terumah in the case
that they have a child. child. So we've totally said all women,
forbidden sex gets them out of the תרומה terumah category. What we're
going to turn back to, turn to tomorrow is how do you
know that it invalidates them from marrying a כהן, Kohen, which is
what's really relevant for us today, okay? And look at that, we
pretty much, I would say we caught up. Yes.
I was wrong about miscarriage rates, they are high enough that the
percentage that we see?
I would've imagined that. I would've imagined that.
So it's like if you're a כהן, Kohen, right? And you have
guests coming over for שבת Shabbos meal. If you're
what?
If you feed your כהנים Kohanim תרומה, Terumah, כהנים Kohanim guests
תרומה, Terumah, only כהנים Kohanim guests.
How could you feed your כהנים Kohanim guest תרומה? Terumah? You מאכיל
ma'achil somebody something טרפה. treif.
Even if this is even if this is your daughter who's now
married to a ישראל, Yisrael, she's just coming home for like a
meal. Yeah, no, she still can't eat it. Right. Because she's completely
out of her father's house.
Exactly. It's not the physical house, it's the household.
Right. Right, I'm saying, but even though like, you know, she's coming
home and. Right. Right. There's no like temporary exception for like, you
know, if she's just coming home for like a meal.
Correct. You talk about a בת כהן Bas Kohen having קדושת הגוף?
Kedushat haGuf?
Yeah, she loses it when she gets married, so what kind of.
Yeah, but then she reverts
to, but essentially does she lose, I mean the whole idea is,
right, is it that she has קדושת הגוף Kedushat haGuf or is
it that she's connected to.
Right, she loses it when she.
Well, yeah, I don't know if you'd say that she loses it
or that her, I mean look, you're right in general to think
about her as קדושת הגוף Kedushat haGuf rather than to think about
her as, you know, that's the question. In a way it's reflected
in the language. Does the גמרא Gemara refer to it as בת
כהן Bas Kohen or as כהנת? Kohenet? Right? You know, בת כהן
Bas Kohen means yes, she has real no status, but because she's
connected the same way her slaves eat and wife eats, so the
daughter of a כהן Kohen eats too. Right. You're saying כהנת Kohenet
and speaking about קדושת הגוף, Kedushat haGuf, thinks about it in a
different way. You're right. And is that to be somehow saying that
even though she has this קדושת הגוף, Kedushat haGuf, I don't know
if you'd say marriage to a ישראל Yisrael removes the קדושה Kedusha
or just, you know, sort of says even though she has the
קדושה Kedusha she's not eating because of her connection to the ישראל
Yisrael household. So Dov, you missed the initial request which is I'm
away Friday, שבת, Shabbos, Sunday. So Michael took Friday. Any possibility you
could take שבת Shabbos or Sunday?
Right. I can take Sunday, if that works. Okay, great.
Any students around?
So I'll ask, yeah, I'll ask one of my students. So he
got Friday and Sunday covered, I will see about getting שבת Shabbos
covered.
Oh, that was my problem.